<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Articles | Sathish Hariharan's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.sathishh.net/blog/categories/articles/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.sathishh.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-09T10:20:54+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://www.sathishh.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sathish Hariharan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open Source Book Discovery App - LocalReads]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.sathishh.net/blog/2014/09/30/Open-Source-Book-Discovery-App/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-30T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://www.sathishh.net/blog/2014/09/30/Open-Source-Book-Discovery-App</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I worked on an idea for discovery of books a couple of years ago. The idea was simple - make a catalog of your paper books
online and tag your location to it. Friends and neighbours would then be able to search for a book using the service and
discover books in your shelf. The service would allow making requests for books and manage subsequent interactions between
users. I tried developing this concept in residential communities, colleges and online book groups but did not get significant
traction to pursue it as a serious business.</p>

<p>In the couple of years that followed there were many others who approached or discussed the same idea online and otherwise.
I discouraged some of the folks explaining my experiences with traction. I am sure many more would want to try it out. But
the fact that there are many people with the same idea points to a possible passionate market however small it maybe. Most of
the code I had developed was lying idle and I thought it would help folks trying to build this concept from scratch if I
open sourced the codebase.</p>

<p>In the last few weeks I refactored the old code and built out a <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.squareprism.localreads.ver1">mobile app</a> with the same backend, but used newer technologies
to build better capabilities and with less code. I have published the app for free on Android platform. You can check it out
at <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.squareprism.localreads.ver1">here</a>. The code is open source and published in github.</p>

<p><img src="/images/localreads-android-page.png" alt="localreads" /></p>

<p>The android app is developed using the <a href="http://www.ionicframework.com">Ionic-Angular framework</a> that lets you build hybrid
(html + native) apps. The backend service is implemented as a set of REST apis using <a href="http://www.grails.org">Grails</a> with
a MongoDB database. You can check out the code on github at the following locations.</p>

<ul>
<li>LocalReads Mobile App Codebase - <a href="https://github.com/sathishc/localreads">https://github.com/sathishc/localreads</a></li>
<li>LocalReads backend service - <a href="https://github.com/sathishc/localreads-service">https://github.com/sathishc/localreads-service</a></li>
</ul>


<p>See instructions for building the codebase in the corresponding github repositories. The front end code uses Protractor/Jasmine for
End-to-End testing and Karma/Jasmine for unit tests. The backend uses Spock framework for testing the apis.</p>

<p>The code base will help developers trying to build similar capabilities for other apps - location
based full-text search, real-time messaging, restful and stateless service, hybrid mobile app using cordova, etc</p>

<p>To build a full stateless restful service in grails I have used the <a href="https://github.com/alvarosanchez/grails-spring-security-rest">Spring Security Rest plugin</a>
as the normal spring security based authentication relies on sessions to be maintained. Real-time messaging is
implemented using <a href="http://grails.org/plugin/spring-websocket">Spring Websockets</a>. Reach out if you are looking for help in these areas.</p>

<p>All of the code is distributed under the Creative Commons License 4.0.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tatkal Nirvana]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.sathishh.net/blog/2014/01/10/Tatkal-NIrvana/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://www.sathishh.net/blog/2014/01/10/Tatkal-NIrvana</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today was special. I logged in at 950AM and found that there were 48 tickets available. I left the window open to keep the session alive. But a few minutes of distraction and at 10 the session had expired!. Oh No!. My heart started beating very fast.</p>

<p>Then I reloaded the site to get the home page. All i could see was the blank page and the spinner icon. I waited patiently (though there was some nail biting) and the page loaded after two minutes. The time was 10:03.</p>

<p>I already had the login / password saved using LastPass. So I clicked login. Nothing. What could be the issue?</p>

<p>I clicked again and to my relief saw the spinner wheel again. I knew I was competing with a few million such requests.</p>

<p>Patience was the key. I took a few deep breaths. 5 minutes. The time is now 10:09AM. And then the page loaded !!</p>

<p>I had memorized the station codes and the dates. I clicked “Find Trains” and this time the page loaded quickly to my surprise. I selected the train. There were still 22 tickets available. I knew I was behind but all was not lost.</p>

<p>I quickly entered the details and chose the best possible credit card options. I knew I needed to 70% probability of completing the reservation. In another couple of minutes I was entering my Citibank IPIN.</p>

<p>I was elated to see the “Redirecting to Merchant” site. I heard the sweet tune of SMS, when money gets deducted from your bank account. But I knew that it was not over…… It was not the finish line yet.</p>

<p>And then it happened. The most beautiful HTML page I have ever seen. Those words which said CONFIRM</p>

<p>Ecstasy. And then. Relief.</p>

<p>If you have not heard of booking a Tatkal ticket. Check out www.irctc.co.in. Or Google “Tatkal Booking”</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Uttarakhand Landscapes]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.sathishh.net/blog/2012/01/09/Uttarakhand-Landscapes/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://www.sathishh.net/blog/2012/01/09/Uttarakhand-Landscapes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We travelled to Uttarakhand during the X&#8217;Mas vacation of 2011 hoping to catch snow. We did not see any snow but some of the places visited were breathtaking in beauty. I want to share details of our trip so others can plan similar trips.</p>

<p><br/><br/>
We had a full-week to spend. Our original plan was to visit Kullu-Manali, but while planning I realized we would either do too much or get bored. So I looked out for similar places that had a chance of snowfall and ended up planning this trip. Our itinerary was Bangalore-Delhi-Dehradun-Mussourie-Uttarkashi-Rishikesh-Haridwar-Delhi-Bangalore. As this blog post is on Uttarakhand landscape, it covers the first 4 days from Mussourie to Haridwar.
<br/><br/>
We took the afternoon flight from Bangalore to make sure we dont end up with cancelled flights due to Delhi winter fog. Our flight landed in Delhi around 5pm and our next connection was the midnight train to Dehradun. As we had a few hour to kill in Delhi, we hired a cab to show us around some of the sights that we had missed in our previous trip to Delhi. We visited India Gate and attempted Lal-Quila. On the way to India gate our cabbie took us around Rashtrapati Bhavan and Rajpath. Delhi was pleasant and beautiful at night.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
    <img style="padding: 5px;" title="India Gate at Night" src="http://www.pixterous.com/Random-Snaps/Random-Snaps/i-TPBbBW3/0/M/Uttkhand-2288-M.jpg" alt="India Gate at Night" />
    <div align="center">India Gate at Night</div>
</p>


<p>After our brief tour of old-Delhi, we ended up at NDLS (New Delhi Station). To our surprise, we found long queues for travellers to get into the station. The queues extended to the road outside and it was freezing. Apparently, one has to get their luggage through a security scanner and hence this queue. The whole process was insane as the scanners were barely attended. People were throwing luggage through the machine and jumping to the other side to grab their baggage and run for the train.</p>

<p><br/><br/>
For someone from Bangalore, the crowd and hassle was overwhelming. Somehow we got through and boarded the night train to Dehradun. The train arrived in Dehradun at 6am sharp.</p>

<p>I had a cab organized through MakeMyTrip for the rest of the journey till Haridwar. To our surprise our taxi was not at the station - when I called him up, the guy says he just woke up and needs to start from Roorkee and it would take 1.5 hrs to reach Dehradun. We had to spend our time freezing in the station until he appeared at 7.30am. It was heavenly to get into the heated Indigo.</p>

<h4>Day-1 (Mussourie)</h4>


<p>Our stay was booked in Mussourie and Dehradun to Mussourie is a pleasant 2 hrs road trip. We stopped at a few places en-route for coffee. The sky was beautiful and I could make some pretty photographs :-)</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
    <img style="padding: 5px;" title="Dawn at highway from Dehradun to Mussourie" src="http://www.pixterous.com/Landscapes/Uttarakhand-India/i-TdQf2Tj/0/M/Uttkhand-2307-M.jpg" alt="Dawn at highway from Dehradun to Mussourie" />
<div align="center">Dawn at highway from Dehradun to Mussourie</div></p>


<p>We stayed at the Padmini Nivas Hotel in Mussourie. Luckily for us we got a room which opened out to the Dehradun valley below. If you are planning to book here - ask for this room (#10 if I remember correctly) as it is the best possible view from this hotel. We checked-in, had a wonderful breakfast (continental and yummy alu-parathas). We spent some time hanging around the resort and then headed to see Kempty falls.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
    <img style="padding: 5px;" title="View of Padmini Nivas" src="http://www.pixterous.com/Random-Snaps/Random-Snaps/i-tLTWNp6/0/M/Uttkhand-2651-M.jpg" alt="View of Padmini Nivas" />
<div align="center">View of Padmini Nivas</div>
</p>


<p>Kempty falls is a crowded, commercial waterfall park which you could easily avoid if you are expecting to see anything natural. But if your spouse is interested in shopping in a flea market, visit this place by all means. I managed to catch some pictures of the falls without people pushing and pulling me. The good experience I remember is having wonderful aloo-tikki&rsquo;s and chai - as it was quite cold, the snack was even more enjoyable. The wife on the other hand had a whale of a time shopping for Tibetan shawls and other stuff that you find in any flea market.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
    <img style="padding: 5px;" title="Kempty Falls" src="http://www.pixterous.com/Landscapes/Uttarakhand-India/i-fVCLbdw/0/M/Uttkhand-2355-M.jpg" alt="Kempty Falls" />
<div align="center">Kempty Falls</div></p>


<p>We headed back to the hotel after a couple of hours and visited the Mussourie Gunhill in the evening. Gunhill is easily accessible from the main Mall road via a cable car. We took a cycle-rickshaw From our hotel to the rope-way and reached in 10 minutes. If you are visiting Mussourie in winter, check out the time of sunset and plan accordingly. The himalayan views from Gunhill is quite beautiful. You can see the late evening colors on the mountains vividly from Gunhill</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
    <img style="padding: 5px;" title="Himalayan view from GunHill" src="http://www.pixterous.com/Landscapes/Uttarakhand-India/i-XVcrRvb/0/M/Uttkhand-2559-M.jpg" alt="Himalayan view from GunHill" />
<div align="center">Himalayan view from GunHill</div>
</p>


<h4>
Day-2 (Dhanaulti)
</h4>


<p>The next day we had planned a trip to Dhanaulti. Dhanaulti is a beautiful valley about 25kms from Mussourie and commands compelling views of himalayas. We visited the eco-park with deodar trees and spent a good 2-3 hours within the park.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
    <img style="padding: 5px;" title="Dhanolti Eco Park" src="http://www.pixterous.com/Landscapes/Uttarakhand-India/i-GZVNGb8/0/M/Uttkhand-2693-M.jpg" alt="Dhanolti Eco Park" />
    <div align="center">Dhanolti Eco Park</div>
</p>


<p>One of the interesting things about Uttarakhand is the unbelievable number of &ldquo;Maggie&rdquo; joints all over - there are Maggi points, Maggi palaces, and Maggi corners everywhere. Needless to say we had maggi at the park.</p>

<p>We hit a place called Lal-tibba (one of the highest points near Mussourie) on our way back from Dhanolti - the ride to lal-tibba was one hell of a journey. I am not sure who was more scared; us or our cab driver - he kept complaining that we should return back to the hotel instead. But we persisted and got to see some magnificent sunset views ever. After the lal-tibba ride, we decided to call it a day.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
    <img style="padding: 5px;" title="Sunset near lal tibba" src="http://www.pixterous.com/Landscapes/Uttarakhand-India/i-MQcMQPh/0/M/Uttkhand-2808-M.jpg" alt="Sunset near lal tibba" />
<div align="center">Sunset near lal tibba</div>
</p>


<h4>
Day-3 (Mussourie to Uttarkashi)
</h4>


<p>We headed to Uttarkashi on the third day. My research with google maps suggested we would have to go through Tehri, but the locals suggested a new road which takes us to Uttarkashi much faster (not in google yet). This route had breathtaking views of the mountains toward Uttarkashi and a major high-light of the trip. If you take this route stop at Tingling point near Mouryana Ramp. The himalayan views here is simply mind boggling. Though most of our journey was pleasant, the construction work on the roads closer to Uttarkashi was a damper. It took us almost 2 hours to cover the last 20 kms. At Uttarkashi we stayed at the <a title="Monal Tourist Home" href="http://www.monaluttarkashi.com/">Monal Tourist Home</a></p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
    <img style="padding: 5px;" title="Himalayas from Mauryana Ramp" src="http://www.pixterous.com/Landscapes/Uttarakhand-India/i-bWxCrVs/0/M/Uttkhand-3024-M.jpg" alt="Himalayas from Mauryana Ramp" />
<div align="center">Himalayas from Mauryana Ramp</div>
</p>




<h4>
Day-4 (Uttarkashi)
</h4>


<p>Monal is a beautiful lodge located a little north of Uttarkashi town. It has a splendid view of the surrounding hills and the Ganges (Assi Ganga) flows very close across the highway. You can hear the water flowing over the rocks from the lodge itself that adds to the experience. I hit the ganges early morning at Monal at around 6:30am to catch the sunrise and the Ganga. The rocks and Ganga is a view that you get all the way from Uttarkashi to Gangotri.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
    <img style="padding: 5px;" title="Ganges next to Monal" src="http://www.pixterous.com/Landscapes/Uttarakhand-India/i-Z2GdjnM/0/M/Uttkhand-3076-M.jpg" alt="Ganges next to Monal" />
<div align="center">Ganges next to Monal</div></p>


<p>Uttarkashi offers many beautiful hikes and treks for serious trekkers and mountaineers. For a family travelling with a 4 year old, there were a couple of treks suggested - 1) trek to Nachiketa Tal and 2) a trek to the waterfall at Barsu. We decided to travel to the waterfall at Barsu. The trip involved a 25km drive to the village of Barsu (at 7000ft) and then a 3km round-trip to the waterfall. The journey to Barsu by the ganga was another fantastic experience. Many hanging bridges cutting across the river provide exceptional photo opportunities. Check out the Nalluna bridge north of the Maneri dam</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img style="padding: 5px;" title="The waterfall at Barsu" src="http://www.pixterous.com/Landscapes/Uttarakhand-India/i-VXwvxJW/0/M/Uttkhand-3164-M.jpg" alt="The waterfall at Barsu" />
<div align="center">The waterfall at Barsu </div></p>




<h4>
Day-5 (Uttarkashi to Haridwar)
</h4>


<p>We started early on this day from Uttarkashi towards Haridwar. The route was via Chamba rather than via Mussourie. This route takes one through a different side of Uttarakhand. We got to see more beautiful views at Dharasu, and Chamba on the way back. The himalayan view from Chamba was the most beautiful of all vintage points and was fitting way to conclude the landscape journey.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img style="padding: 5px;" title="Himalayas from Chamba" src="http://www.pixterous.com/Landscapes/Uttarakhand-India/i-Hsr36QF/0/M/Uttkhand-3285-M.jpg" alt="Himalayas from Chamba" />
<div align="center">Himalayas from Chamba </div></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
